Guide to the Henry Hallam Tweedy Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Henry Hallam Tweedy Papers
1895-1953
RG 131
Yale University Divinity School Library
6
(15 boxes)
Writings and sermons of Tweedy document his theology and his career at Yale. Henry Hallam Tweedy (1868-1953) was professor of practical theology at the Yale Divinity School for thirty years.
Tweedy, Henry Hallam, 1868-1953
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Tweedy family.
Biographical / Historical
Henry Hallam Tweedy (1868-1953), a native of Binghamton, New York, was professor of practical theology at the Yale Divinity School from 1909 to 1937. He received his Bachelor's and Master's degrees from Yale and also attended Union Theological Seminary and the University of Berlin. A Congregational minister, he occupied pulpits in Utica, New York and Bridgeport before joining the Yale faculty in 1909. He was awarded an honorary doctorate by Lebanon Valley College in 1921. Tweedy was acting dean of the Yale Divinity School from 1934 to 1935. He compiled the hymnal Christian Worship and Praise and wrote or co-authored the books Moral and Religious Training in the School and Home, Religion and War, and Training the Devotional Life.
Scope and Contents
There is little personal material in this collection, but Tweedy's writings, sermons, and course-related material provide excellent documentation of the theology and methods of one of the Yale Divinity School's most renowned professors of practical theology.
Nearly 400 manuscript sermons by Tweedy are contained in the collection. Places and dates preached are noted on the individual envelopes containing the sermons. A full list of sermon titles is provided only for the first two boxes. Themes addressed by Tweedy reflect the issues of war, urbanization, and morality of concern to American society during the first few decades of the twentieth century.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1922-1928
II. Writings, 1895-1940, n.d.
III. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1924-1953, n.d.
IV. Notes and Course-Related Material, 1902-1938
Educators; Tweedy, Henry Hallam, 1868-1953; Yale University. Divinity School
- Correspondence, 1922-1928; Series I
  - From Channing Pollock, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - From J. Robert Halmshaw, 1922-1928 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - To Bruce Curry, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Writings, 1895-1940, n.d.; Series II
  - Personal writings
    - Hymns, prayers, poems, stories, Christmas greetings (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Published writings
    - "Frank Talks with Honest Doubters", 1904 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Making Prayer Real" ( International Journal of Religious Education ), 1934 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Making Devotional Reading Real" ( International Journal of Religious Education ), 1934 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Is there a Reasonable Basis for a Belief in Personal Survival?" ( The Pilgrim Highroad ), 1935 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Sermons
    - "Abimelech", 1899 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Academic occasions, 1896-1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "The Acknowledgment of God That Counts", 1900 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Address to Church in Search of a Pastor", 1920 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Adjustment to God", 1933 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Ahasurrus: The Nemesis of Vick", 1900 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Ageless Calvary", 1899 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "The Aloneness of the Soul", 1900 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Amusements" (Address), 1931 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Anarchy", 1901 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "The Answer of Grace", 1902 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "The Answer is an Ungranted Prayer", 1908 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "The Arithmetic of Character", 1898 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "The Art of Life", 1901 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "An Artist's Conceptions of the Gospel: The Christ of Tissot", 1900 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "Atherton's Resurrection", 1901 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "In the Authority of Gashmu", 1902 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Baked Lives", 1933 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "The Battle Cry of Progress", 1899 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "The Battle for Brotherhood", 1904 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "The Beatitude of Endurance", 1905 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "The Beatitude of the Peace Makers", 1907 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "The Beauty of Holiness", 1904 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Benjamin", 1899 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "The Best Degree", 1924 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "The Bible and Science", 1923 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "The Bible of Today", 1901 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Bible Studies", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "The Biography of the Devil" (Lecture), 1901 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "The Book of Life", 1904 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Books and the Spiritual Life", 1906 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "The Bridge of San Luis Rey", 1930 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Bridgeport's Real Four Hundred", 1908 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Browning's 'My Star': The Revelations of Love", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Business Men and the Bible", 1926 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Business Methods in Church Affairs", 1899 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "But", 1905 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "A Call for Volunteers", 1895 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Can I Believe in God the Father?", 1904 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Causing the Dragons to Praise God", 1942 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "The Challenge of Easter", 1928 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "The Challenge of the Modern World to the Ministry", 1906 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "The Challenge Presented to the Preacher by the Modern Mind", 1913 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "The Chambers of Imagery", 1909 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Chapel Talks I-IV, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - "Character and Creed", 1902 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "Characteristics of Christian Faith", 1898 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "Charge to the People", 1910 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "The Child and the Bible School", 1902 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - "The Child and the Pastor" (2 lectures), 1908 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - "Child Labor: A Statement and an Appeal", 1907 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Children's Day Talks, 1899-1904 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Children's Sermons, 1901-1921 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - "The Choice of the Soul" (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - "Christ All" - Commemorative Addresses (Box 3, Folder 14-19)
    - "The Commission of a Conqueror" - "The Duty of Transfiguration" (Box 4, Folder 20-24)
    - "Dying to Live" - "Gideon" (Box 5, Folder 24a-28)
    - "The Glory of Young Men" - "How to Hear a Good Sermon" (Box 6, Folder 29-33)
    - "How to Read the Bible" - "Jesus as Executive" (Box 7, Folder 34-38)
    - "Jesus' Way" - "Majoring in Minors" (Box 8, Folder 39-42)
    - "Makers of Holidays" - "Move On" (Box 9, Folder 43-47)
    - "Music and Religion" - "The Problem of the City" (Box 10, Folder 48-52)
    - "Project Method in Preaching" - "Selfish Sympathy" (Box 11, Folder 53-56)
    - "The Sermon of the Cloister" - Thanksgiving addresses (Box 12, Folder 57-62)
    - "Things Left Unsaid" - "What is the Church" (Box 13, Folder 63-67)
    - "What is the Good of Going to Church" - "The Young Man Who Stood By" (Box 14, Folder 68-71)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1924-1953, n.d.; Series III
  - Including photographs, diary, obituary, 1924, 1953, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 72)
  - Framed reproduction of Tweedy portrait (Box OV-d6)
- Notes and Course-Related Material, 1902-1938, n.d.; Series IV
  - Printed material organized by subjects such as prayer, prohibition, 1910-1930, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 73-76)
  - Notes for sermons and talks, 1902-1911,1935 (Box 15, Folder 77-80)
  - Notes on Books, 1921-1925 (Box 15, Folder 81-82)
  - Class schedules and sermon schedules, 1927-1938 (Box 15, Folder 83)
  - Course Bibliographies, 1935-1936, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 83)